-Hey. Who wants French toast? -I'll have some.
-谁要法国吐司？ -给我一点
Me too. Eggs and milk in the fridge. Thanks.
我也要，牛奶和鸡蛋在冰箱里 谢谢
-What's the matter? -My hand feels weird.
-怎么回事？ -我的手怪怪的
I guess it's because I'm engaged!
因为订婚的关系吧！
-When will that start getting annoying? -Start?
-什么时候会开始变得烦人？ -开始？
Let's start the wedding plans.
开始计划婚礼吧
-Okay. -Already?
-好 -现在就开始？
We got a lot to do. We gotta think about the flowers,the music..
有很多事要做，要想花的安排 音乐…
-I have thoughts on the music. -Too many cooks...
-我觉得音乐的安排… -钱德，太多厨师了
Take it from me. All you have to do is show up and say the right name.
给你良心的建议 你只需要出现，说对名字就好了
-What in God's name is that? -Oh,my God,the wedding book?
-那是什么？ -老天，是婚礼计划书？
I haven't seen that since 4th grade.
四年级后我就没看到它了
This baby has everything. Take, you know, locations for instance:
这里面什么都有 比如说，地点：
First organized alphabetically, then geographically...
先以字母顺序排列 再以地理位置排列…
then by square footage.
然后以大小排列
That is so smart.
好聪明
Break it off. Break it off,now.
快溜，快溜，就是现在
The One With Rachel's Book
本集播出：瑞秋的婚礼计划书
rainystar压制iPod-MP4
That conclusively proves...
以上证明了…
that I had the idea for Jurassic Park first.
《侏罗纪公园》是我想到的
Let's take a look..
我们来看看…
Phoebe,what are you doing here?
菲比，你来干什么？
I need to talk to you. It's urgent. It's about Monica and Chandler.
我有事和你说，很紧急 有关摩妮卡和钱德
Oh,my God. Of course.
我的天，当然
Would you please excuse me for a moment?
等我一下
Do you know each other's hometowns? Why don't you..?
你们知道彼此从哪儿来的吗？ 何不…？
What's going on?
怎么回事？
Well,not much. I was just thinking that since they just got engaged...
没什么，我在想 他们刚订婚…
it would be nice if they have privacy.
应该多给他们一些独处的时间
So could I just move in with you for a couple days?
我可以搬去你家几天吗？
Okay,sure. But what's wrong with Monica and Chandler?
好，当然，摩妮卡和钱德 发生了什么事吗？
Nothing. Why?
没事，怎么了？
You said it was urgent.
你说很紧急的
Yeah,it is. My movie starts in five minutes.
是啊，我的电影5分钟后 要开演了
Do you realize I have a classroom full of students?
你知道我有一屋子的学生在这儿吗？
Oh,I'm sorry. I'm so rude. Does anyone want to come to the movie?
抱歉，我很没礼貌 有人想要一起去看电影吗？
I haven't cleared the budget with my parents...
我还没和我爸妈谈到预算…
but how's this for music?
不过音乐部份的安排 这样好不好？
A string quartet for the processional, a jazz trio for cocktails...
行进时用弦乐四重奏 鸡尾酒会时安排爵士三重奏…
the Bay City Rollers for dancing...
跳舞时用湾市摇滚…
Wait, that was for my 6th grade wedding.
等一下，那是我的六年级婚礼
You couldn't get them anyway. Ian doesn't play anymore,and Derek...
也不可能用他们 伊恩不演出了，德芮克…
Derek is a name I shouldn't know.
我不该知道德芮克这个人的
Mon,do you have another pillow, something a little snugglier?
摩妮卡，有没有别的枕头 比较舒服一点的？
Why are you napping here instead of at your place?
你为什么不回去你家 要在这里睡？
-The duck. -What,the duck?
-因为鸭子 -什么，鸭子？
What the hell did the damn duck do now?
怎么，现在鸭子又做了什么？
Well,he did not get sick somewhere in there...
它不是在那里生病的…
and it was immediately found and properly cleaned up.
而且立刻被发现 并妥当处理干净了
Do I get to look at this...
我可以看吗…
or is it just for people involved in the wedding?
还是只有婚礼相关人员可以看？
Of course you can look at it. I want your opinion.
你当然可以看，我要你的意见
Here you go.
来
-What about centerpieces? -Centerpieces!
-桌子中间的花饰？ -桌子中间的花饰！
-Roses or lilies? -Definitely roses.
-玫瑰还是百合？ -当然是玫瑰
I think they're more "wedding-y."
我觉得它们比较像婚礼用花
-But lilies are the clear choice. -Oh,my God,it's like one mind.
-但很清楚应该选百合 -老天，简直就是同一个脑袋
Guys, guys, you gotta let me nap.
各位，各位，让我休息好不好
I'm gonna get cranky.
不然我会脾气不好
Joey,there's a perfectly good couch across the hall.
乔伊，走廊对面有很好的沙发
Yes,it is perfectly good...
是很不错…
and it is not one of the places the duck got sick.
但那不是鸭子生病的地方之一
What?
什么？
-All right,I'm gonna go. -Joey,what did the duck do?
-好，我要走了 -乔伊，鸭子到底做了什么？
I don't know, but he did not eat your face cream.
我不知道，但他没吃你的面霜
Hey,little buddy. How you feeling?
小朋友，你觉得如何？
What the hell is in that face cream?
那面霜里到底有什么？
That's so soft.
好软
Pillowcases!
有枕头套耶！
"Zelda looked at the chimney sweep. Her father,the vicar.."
“柔达看着扫烟囱的人 她的父亲是个传道者…”
Vicar?
传道者？
"wouldn't be home for hours.
还有好几小时才会回来
Her loins were burning.
她欲火中烧
She threw caution to the wind and reached out and grabbed his.."
她不顾一切伸出手去抓住他的…
This is a dirty book!
这是色情小说！
Phoebe?
菲比？
Oh,Ross,hi.
嗨，罗斯
-Phoebe,what are you doing? -Sorry,I'm with a client right now.
-菲比，你在干什么？ -抱歉，我有客人在
-Phoebe! -Okay,let's talk outside.
-菲比！ -好吧，我们在外面谈
Phoebe,you can't massage people in my apartment.
你不可以在我家帮人家按摩
I did it at Monica and Chandler's.
我在摩妮卡和钱德家都可以
And they knew about it?
他们知道吗？
Okay, Ross, what is this really about?
好吧，罗斯，到底怎么回事？
This is my home,and I want to be able to come and go when I want.
这是我家，我希望能自由出入
I will find someplace else to do the rest of my appointments.
我会找其他地方 来做我其他的客人
What's the big deal?
这有什么大不了的？
I don't want naked, greasy strangers in my apartment...
我不要光着身子 身上油油的陌生人在我家…
when I want to kick back with a puzzle.. Beer,cold beer.
当我想回家放松 拿一片拼图…啤酒，冰啤酒
Hey,Joey. What are you doing?
嘿，乔伊，你好吗？
Sweeping. Why? Does it turn you on?
扫地，怎么？ 引起你的性趣吗？
No.
不会
What if I was sweeping a chimney?
如果我扫的是烟囱呢？
Joey,did you eat my face cream?
乔伊，你吃了我的面霜吗？
Where are you going? The vicar won't be home for hours.
你去那儿？ 传道者要几小时后才会回来
Joey, where did you learn that word?
乔伊，你从那儿学到那个字？
Where do you think...
你想是哪里…
Zelda?
柔达？
-You found my book?! -Yeah,I did!
-你看了我的书？！ -对！
Joey, what are you doing going into my bedroom?
乔伊，你到我房里干什么？
I'm sorry. I know I shouldn't have, but you got porn!
抱歉，我知道我不应该 可是你有色情小说！
You know what? I don't care. I'm not ashamed of my book.
知道吗？我不在乎 我不觉得我的书丢脸
There's nothing wrong with a woman enjoying a little erotica.
女人享受一点情色没什么不对
It's a healthy expression of female sexuality...
是女性性感的健康表达…
which,by the way,is something that you will never understand.
你永远都不会了解的
You got porn.
你有色情小说
-Hello. -Hi,is Phoebe here?
-你好 -菲比在吗？
-No,she's out for the night. -Oh,great!
-不，今晚她不在 -真是的！
Can I help you with something?
可以帮忙你吗？
I don't know. Are you a masseur?
我不知道，你是按摩师吗？
Yes,I am.
是，我是
Great! Dad?
太好了！爸？
Thank you so much. I'll pick him up in an hour.
谢谢你，一小时后我来接他
Your parents must've been thrilled when you told them you were engaged.
你父母听到你订婚一定很开心
Oh, yeah. I should probably call them.
哦，是啊 我应该打电话给他们
I remember when we first got engaged.
我记得我们刚订婚的时候
-I've never heard that story. -Dad..
-我没听过这个故事 -爸…
Well,I'd gotten Judy pregnant.
茱蒂怀孕了
I still don't know how.
我还是不知道怎么发生的
You don't know how? Your dog thought my diaphragm was a chew toy.
你不知道怎么发生的？你的狗 以为我的避孕器是磨牙玩具
What a sweet story.
真感人的故事
You're not hearing it at your 5th grade Halloween party.
至少你不是在五年级的 万圣节宴会听到这故事的
They wanted a scary story.
他们要听吓人的故事
We're excited about our wedding plans.
我们对婚礼计划很兴奋
Pretty soon we'll be making a big withdrawal from the wedding fund.
很快我们就要从婚礼基金 提一大笔钱
-What? -You tell her,Jack. I can't do it.
-什么？ -杰克，你告诉她，我做不到
You have the wedding fund, don't you?
你们有婚礼基金，对吧？
We have it. Only now we call it "the beach house."
我们有，只是现在叫做 “海滩别墅”
You spent my wedding fund on the beach house?
你把我的婚礼基金 花在海滩别墅？
We're sorry. We assumed...
对不起，我们以为…
that when you turned 30 you'd pay for it yourself.
等你30岁后，你会自己付的
You bought the beach house when I was 23.
你们买海滩别墅时我才23岁
So you've had seven years of beach fun...
你在海边享受了7年好时光…
and you can't put a price on that.
那可是无价的
We do feel bad about this.
我们觉得很抱歉
We saved again when you dated Richard.
你和理查交往时 我们又开始存钱
Then that went to hell, so we redid the kitchen.
结果你们闹翻了 我们重新装璜了厨房
What about Chandler?
那钱德呢？
It was Chandler. We didn't think he'd propose.
我们以为钱德不会求婚
I didn't start drinking enough at the start of the meal.
开始吃饭时，酒喝得不够
I can't believe there's no money.
我不相信竟然没有钱让我结婚
Maybe,if your father hadn't tried...
也许还有，如果你爸没有…
to sell ice over the lnternet.
在网路卖冰的话
-It seemed like such a simple idea. -Stupid. The word is "stupid."
-那个主意看来很简单 -笨，只能用“笨”来形容
Enough. I don't want to hear about it anymore.
够了，我不想再听了
Good luck, Chandler.
钱德，祝你好运
Okay, now I'm going to...
好，现在我要…
touch you.
碰你了
That's soft.
好软
Do you think your parents could help pay for it?
你的父母可能帮忙付吗？
I don't know.
我不知道
My mother spent most of her money on her fourth wedding.
我妈大部份的钱 都花在她第四次的婚礼了
Saving the rest for her divorce.
剩下的钱她离婚要用
And any extra cash my father has, he saves for his yearly trips to...
而我爸存的钱用在…
Dollywood.
到桃利屋的年度旅行
-What happened at dinner? -My parents spent the wedding fund.
-你们吃饭发生什么事了？ -我父母把婚礼基金花掉了
My God,what did you order?
我的天，你点了什么菜？
Wait,there's no money? Well,this is terrible.
等一下，没有婚礼基金了？ 太惨了
You guys will have to get married in,like,a rec center.
你们必须在活动中心结婚了
-Honey,it's gonna be okay. -No,it's not gonna be okay.
-亲爱的，没关系的 -不，有关系
-No swing band,no lilies. -It's gonna be okay.
-没有乐团，没有百合 -那很好啊
I mean,you don't need to have this...
你不需要有这种…
rustic ltalian feast.
意大利野宴
You don't need this custom-made...
你不需要这种订做的…
empire waist,duchess satin gown.
帝国式腰线，公主型丝缎礼服
You can wear off-the-rack.
你可以买现成的礼服
It's really gonna be okay.
真的不会有问题的
The important thing is, we love each other and we're gonna get married.
重要的是我们彼此相爱，要结婚了
Do you even understand what "off-the-rack" means?
你知不知道“现成的”是什么意思？
Why don't you pay for it yourself?
你为什么不自己付钱呢？
I don't have any money.
怎么付？我没钱
-I have some. -How much?
-我有 -多少？
Well, close to...
将近有…
-Are you kidding me?! -How much?
-你开玩笑？！ -多少？
-Enough for wedding scenario A. -Really?
-够办婚礼计划A -真的？
How great are you, you little saver!
你真好，努力存钱的人！
This is exactly the budget of my dream wedding.
正是理想婚礼的预算
You guys are so made for each other.
你们是天造地设的一对
You're not suggesting we spend all the money on the wedding?
你不是要把所有的钱 都花在婚礼上吧？
Yeah.
是啊
Look,Mon,I've been saving this money for six years...
我花了六年存到这些…
and I have some of it earmarked for the future,not just for a party.
有些是将来要用的 不是都花在一场宴会上的
Wow! Hello, Mr. Chandler.
钱德先生，你好啊
Sweetie, this is the most special day of our lives.
甜心，这是我们一生中 最重要的一天
I realize that, honey, but I won't spend all the money on one party.
我知道，甜心 但我不要把钱都花在一场宴会上
Honey,I love you.
甜心，我爱你
But if you call our wedding a party one more time...
但如果你再叫我们的婚礼 一场宴会…
you may not get invited.
你可能不会被邀请
We can always earn more money. We're only gonna get married once.
钱可以再赚，我们只结婚一次
I understand,but I have to put my foot down. The answer is no.
我了解，但我非常坚决 我的答案是不
You're gonna have to put your foot down?
你很坚决？
Yes,I am.
对，我是
Money and a firm hand.
有钱和有一只坚定的手
Finally a Chandler I can get onboard with.
终于是我可以认同的钱德了
（中央公园咖啡厅）
-Hey,Rach. -Joey.
-嘿，瑞秋 -乔伊
Hey, Rach, do you smell smoke?
有没有闻到烟味？
I get it. Smoke, chimney, chimney sweep. Very funny. Ha,ha.
我懂了，烟，烟囱 扫烟囱的人，很好笑
No,no,I'm serious. You don't smell it?
不，不，我说真的 你没闻到？
Something's on fire.
有东西着火了
I don't smell anything.
我没闻到什么
You know what? It's probably just your burning loins.
你知道吗？可能是你雄雄的欲火
-Hey,what are you guys talking about? -Nothing.
-你们在讲什么？ -没什么
Damn,this coffee's cold.
讨厌，咖啡冷了
Do you mind if I heat this on your loins?
可以在你身上加温一下吗？
You know, I cannot believe you told him. Joey...
乔伊，你竟然告诉了他…
I guess you bought that book after we broke up.
我猜你在我们分手后买了那本书
I did,because I wore out my first copy when I was with you.
是啊，因为第一本 在我们交往时被翻烂了
Oh,yeah?
是吗？
Well,when we were going out, I read tons of porno magazines.
我们交往时 我看了一大堆色情杂志
Sup?
怎么样？
Ross, how could you do that to an old man?
罗斯，你怎么可以 那样对待一位老先生？
Excuse me,ladies.
对不起，小姐们
I'm sorry?
什么啊？
My massage client. Arthur.
我的按摩客人，亚瑟
His daughter said some guy that worked for me...
他女儿说替我工作的一个人…
gave him a really weird massage.
替他做了很奇怪的按摩
I gave him an extremely professional massage.
我做了很专业的按摩
He said you poked at him with wooden spoons.
他说你用木汤匙戳他
Okay,so it wasn't a traditional massage.
好吧，不是传统的按摩
But I did give him acupressure with a pair of chopsticks...
可是我有用筷子替他刺激穴道…
and I gently exfoliated him with a mop.
温和地用拖把去角质
Well,he's never coming back. You just cost me $80 a week.
他再也不会来了 你害我一星期少进帐八十元
This is your fault. You didn't move his appointment.
是你的错 你没更改他约的时间
Oh,it's my fault? You didn't have to massage him.
我的错？你不必替他按摩的
You could've sent him away.
你可以请他回去的
You could've not rolled Tonka trucks up and down his back.
你不必用玩具推土机 在他背上滚来滚去
He said he liked that!
他说他很喜欢！
You're right, you're right. I'm sorry.
你对，你对，对不起
Dude,what are you massaging an old man for?
你干嘛按摩一位老先生？
-His daughter was hot. -Gotcha.
-他女儿很辣 -懂了
Listen...
听着…
I've been thinking.
我想过了
It's not fair of me to ask you to spend all your money on our wedding.
要你把所有的钱 花在婚礼上很不公平
I mean,you work really hard for that.
你很辛苦才赚来的
-Well. -Well,you work for that.
-嗯 -你赚来的
Look, I've thought about it too.
我也想过了
I'm sorry. I think we should spend all the money on the wedding.
对不起，我们应该把钱花在婚礼的
-You do? -Yeah,I'm putting my foot down.
-真的？ -对，我很坚决
Look,when I proposed, I told you...
当我求婚时，我告诉你…
that I would do anything to make you happy.
我会尽力让你快乐
And if having the perfect wedding makes you happy...
如果办一场完美婚礼 能让你开心…
then that's what we're gonna do.
我们就这么做
You are so sweet.
你对我真好
What about the future and stuff?
那未来怎么办呢？
Forget about the future and stuff.
管他呢
So we only have two kids.
我们只生两个就好
We'll pick our favorite and that one will get to go to college.
选一个我们最喜欢的 让他去念大学
-Have you thought about that? -Yeah.
-你想过这些？ -对
How many kids were we gonna have?
你本来要几个孩子？
Four. A boy, twin girls and another boy.
四个，一个男孩，一对双胞胎女儿 再一个男孩
What else did you think about?
你还想过什么？
Well,stuff like where we'd live, you know.
还有我们要住的地方
Like a small place outside the city...
像是在市中心外的小房子…
where our kids could learn to ride their bikes.
我们的小孩可以学骑单车
We could have a cat that had a bell on its collar...
可以养只猫咪 脖子上挂着铃铛…
and we could hear it every time it ran through the little kitty door.
每次它跑出小门时 都听得见铃声
We'd have an apartment over the garage where Joey could grow old.
在车库上盖个房间 让乔伊终老
You know what?
你知道吗？
I don't want a big,fancy wedding.
我不要一个盛大的婚礼
-Sure you do. -No.
-你要的 -不
I want everything that you've just said. I want a marriage.
我要你刚刚说的每一样东西 我要一个婚姻
You sure?
你确定？
-I love you so much. -I love you.
-我好爱你 -我爱你
When you were talking about our future,you said cat.
你刚说到将来的时候 你说猫咪
But you meant dog,right?
你指的是狗，对不对？
-Totally. -Good.
-对 -好
Hello, Zelda.
你好，柔达
-Who are you supposed to be? -The vicar.
-你又是谁呢？ -传道者
-Do you even know what a vicar is? -Like a goalie, right?
-你知道传道者是什么吗？ -像是个守门员，对不对？
Look, that's enough.
乔伊，我是说真的，够了
You make stupid jokes and sleazy innuendoes...
你老是开这些笨玩笑 还有无聊的暗讽…
-and it's just not funny anymore. -I'm sorry. Rach,I'm sorry.
-真的是不好笑 -对不起，瑞秋，对不起
Maybe I could make it up to you by taking you roughly in the barn.
也许我可以在谷仓里 粗暴地对待你来补偿你
All right, that's it. You want to do it? Let's do it.
好了，够了 你想做吗？我们做吧
That's right. I want to do it with you.
没错，我想和你做
Been trying to fight it, but you said all the right things.
我一直想抗拒，但你说的每一句话 都深深打动了我
I did?
我有吗？
Yeah, I been waiting for so long to get on that body.
有，我想得到你的身体想了好久
-This body? -Yeah,that's right.
-我的身体？ -对，没错
Come on, Joey, sex me up.
乔伊，放马过来吧
You're starting to sound like the butcher's wife in chapter seven.
你听起来开始像 第七章里的屠夫妻子
Come on, now. Don't keep me waiting. Take your clothes off.
来吧，不要让我等 脱掉你的衣服
But I'd keep that helmet on, because you're in for a rough ride.
但留着你的头盔 这是一场狂风暴雨
I don't want to. I'm scared.
我不要，我好害怕